<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: opinion | Prospectus Journal]]></title>
  <link href="http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/blog/categories/opinion/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-30T23:16:14-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zarrar Shehzad]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Arshavsky 2006]]></title>
    <link href="http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/blog/2013/12/30/arshavsky-2006/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-30T22:26:55-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/blog/2013/12/30/arshavsky-2006</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This article puts forth the hypothesis that long-term consolidation occurs via modification of DNA in individual neurons. I wonder if an alternative to having DNA explain the persistence of a memory trace is the replay of memories that occurs during system consolidation. One can imagine if the neural system loops over the same trace, it potentially can strengthen the connections via synaptic consolidation over time. Furthermore, sleep might help do this same thing, replay or refresh different memories to allow for continual maintenance.</p>

<p>For work on the stability of synaptic connections see Grutzendler et al., 2002; Zuo et al., 2005; De Paola et al., 2006.</p>

<h2 id="flaws-in-model">Flaws In Model</h2>

<p>He begins with a discussion about how the traditional model can’t explain how you can retain your old memories when you have an epileptic seizure since this should change all your memories. Similarly he claims it’s difficult to understand how something that is ever-changing like proteins maintaining the memories of those who can remember almost everything.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Since proteins have a very short lifetime as compared with memory lifetime, additional hypotheses are required to explain how stable synaptic modifications could result from a transient activation of the protein synthesis.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>He then strangely claims that</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>…memory reactivation must lead to further modification in synaptic connections and, eventually, to memory erosion, in direct correlation to how frequently it is accessed.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>and concludes</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Since this is not the case, and repetitive retrievals lead to memory strengthening rather than erosion, we must conclude that memory is resistant to the synaptic activity that accompanies memory retrieval.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This conclusion is strange because I thought that was the point, repeated retrieval and encoding leads to strengthening of the connection via reactivation and the hebbian rule.</p>

<p>Another bad example, he gives is about the issue of spontaneous neural activity.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>According to SPH, we must expect that ongoing spontaneous activity will lead to incessant, uncontrolled modifications in synaptic connections, and eventually, to erosions in older memories.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>But the glitch in his argument is that spontaneous activity happens amongst the current connections. True there is some noise but really this might strengthen the already existent connections.</p>

<p>Another oddity is that he claims that</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>…memory retrieval cannot occur through the reactivation of the same neural assemblies that are involved in initial learning, because these two processes have different localizations</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Yes, but it isn’t cut and dry like this. Instead the weights just shift from hippocampus to neocortex, the hippocampus can still be involved. Also even for a recent memory, the involvement of the hippocampus is accompanied by involved of distal neocortical regions.</p>

<p>But I think the claim is just that:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>…primary synaptic consolidation in the MTL and persistent system consolidation in the neocortex may have radically different mechanisms.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>He does raise some interesting points about how issues with Alzheimer’s isn’t related to LTP stuff. Not sure if he is missing some facts like structural changes that occur with synaptic consolidation.</p>

<h2 id="dna-hypothesis">DNA Hypothesis</h2>

<p>I don’t totally get this hypothesis as he doesn’t explain the mechanism that clearly. It seems like it would have something to do with somatic DNA recombination. And he notes that</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>blockage of enzymes participating in the process of somatic DNA recombination impairs learning and memory consolidation (Colon-Cesario et al., 2006; McGowan et al., 2004; Pena de Ortiz et al., 2003; Ren and Pena de Ortiz, 2002; Wang et al., 2003).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Another hypothesis states that</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Epigenetic modifications alter the structure of the chromatin due to chemical changes to the DNA or histones without change the DNA nucleotide sequence…(Chwang et al., 2005; Levenson et al., 2004)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don’t totally get how these processes can’t be altered or undone. For instance, shouldn’t additional consolidation eventually alter these DNA-related modifications?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
