<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: systems | Prospectus Journal]]></title>
  <link href="http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/blog/categories/systems/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-12T18:43:21-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zarrar Shehzad]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Girardeau 2011]]></title>
    <link href="http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/blog/2014/01/05/girardeau-2011/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-05T17:08:46-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/blog/2014/01/05/girardeau-2011</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Basically this article suggests that a mechanism for consolidation can consistent of sharp wave-ripples that occur periodically in slow-wave fluctuations. The bursts of activity that occur with these ripples may act to ‘reinforce’ recent experiences and engage more long-term memory storage machinery. For instance, this strong firing could turn on some prion-like machinery that leads to persistent maintenance of memory-induced changes in the circuitry.</p>

<h2 id="stage-model-of-memory-formation">2-Stage Model of Memory Formation</h2>

<p>Based on Buzsaki’s work [see 6,7], they describe memory formation as </p>

<blockquote>
  <ol>
    <li>novel information is first encoded during the waking state</li>
    <li>then consolidated during subsequent sleep</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<p>During alert wakefulness [see 8]:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>higher levels of neuromodulators such as acetylcholine in the hippocampus enhance the influence of external inputs relative to intrinsic activity, likely favoring sensory processing and predominant information flow from the neocortex to the hippocampus</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="sharp-wave-ripples-swprs">Sharp Wave-Ripples (SWPRs)</h2>

<p>Happens during slow wave sleep and quiet wakefulness. Massive endogenous activation of large neuronal populations at repeated but irregular intervals that</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Provide the strong synaptic bombardment necessary for the induction of long term synaptic changes</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Occur at 0.01-2HZ and when they occur they have high population frequency of firing (150-200Hz). More details about how the ripples, propogate through the hippocampus are found in the paper.</p>

<p>[TODO: add some of the figures from the paper]</p>

<h2 id="replay-and-synaptic-plasticity">Replay and Synaptic Plasticity</h2>

<p>Relate SWPRs to replay and off-line memory consolidation.</p>

<p><span class="fluo">I wonder if the ripples particularly the slow-wave stuff can be measured with fMRI? Or maybe that is what we are measuring during awake consolidation? </span></p>

<p><p class='info info' data-title='Question'>I wonder if the ripples particularly the slow-wave stuff can be measured with fMRI? Or maybe that is what we are measuring during awake consolidation?</p></p>

<p>The idea here is that weakly depolarized cells during encoding can then lead to a persistent memory by strong replay later. It appears that this replay does happen during slow-wave sleep (SWS) [see 44-46]. Reactivations would involve broader brain regions, including the thalamus and neocortex.</p>

<p>One issue here is that many of these studies were done on highly trained animals so learning per say did not occur.</p>

<h2 id="swprs-and-consolidation">SWPRs and Consolidation</h2>

<p>Suppressing the ripples impairs consolidation [57].</p>

<h2 id="hippocampo-neocortical-information-transfer">Hippocampo-Neocortical Information Transfer</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>Successful retrieval becomes increasingly dependent on neocortical areas, in particular the prefrontal and anterior cingulate cortices [see 59,60]</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="slow-or-fast">Slow or Fast?</h3>

<p>Unclear however if this transition from hippocampus to neocortex is always slow with some evidence of rapid consolidation when new information is incorporated into a pre-existing cortical network of similar traces (i.e., a schema) [63].</p>

<h3 id="oscillations">Oscillations</h3>

<p>Initial encoding is done at theta oscillations for transfer between hippocampus and superficial layers of retrohippocampal  (entorhinal, subicular, presubicular, and parasubicular) areas. In the deep layers of the retrohippocampal cortices, which relay hippocampal outputs to the neocortex, are modulated by SPWRs.</p>

<h2 id="awake-replay">Awake Replay?</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>Most reactivations during awake SPWRs occur in reverse order when the animal receives a water reward at the end of a trajectory [80], reactivations were also found to anticipate the subsequent trajectory (in forward order) when the animal was about to start running again [84].</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Suggestion is made that maybe awake replay plays a slightly different role in consolidation…although it is unclear what that difference is to me.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Neuronal sequences corresponding to remote trajectories [86] as well as routes never experience before (‘shortcuts’) [88] have also been reported.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="synaptic-downscaling-alternate-hypothesis">Synaptic Downscaling (Alternate Hypothesis)</h2>

<p>Posits that </p>

<blockquote>
  <p>SWS promotes a global synaptic downscaling necessary to avoid saturation of synaptic strengths [90,91].</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s interesting that this hypothesis is consistent with that other paper [todo: find] that finds greater resting connectivity in memory retrieval related areas in the evening than in the morning.</p>

<p>However, a problem with the downscaling hypothesis is that</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>it would predict a progressive increase in firing rates during the awake state, followed by a commensurate decrease during sleep. yet, the overall firing rate in the hippocampus is maintained over time.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This issue is great for me as it provides a potentially contrasting hypothesis on what might be expected to occur over the course of awake consolidation.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
