<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: synaptic | Prospectus Journal]]></title>
  <link href="http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/blog/categories/synaptic/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-12T18:43:21-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zarrar Shehzad]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Medina 2008]]></title>
    <link href="http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/blog/2014/01/12/medina-2008/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-12T17:06:12-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/blog/2014/01/12/medina-2008</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="do-memories-consolidate-to-persist-or-do-they-persist-to-consolidate">Do memories consolidate to persist or do they persist to consolidate?</h1>

<h2 id="background">Background</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>Ribot…first to envisage that memories might be processed over time (…Ribot gradient)</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Muller and Pilzecker were the first to use the term consolidation to describe the post-acquisition processes that stabilize memories thus explaining retroactive interference</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="questions">Questions</h3>

<ol>
  <li>Which is the time course of memory consolidation?</li>
  <li>Is consolidation a unitary process?</li>
  <li>What are the brain regions engaged in consolidation?</li>
  <li>How can the brain form persistent memories?</li>
  <li>How is information in structures of the MTL transferred for ultimate consolidation in the neocortex?</li>
</ol>

<p>And why this sequence of events occurs in some but not all memories?</p>

<h3 id="invertebrates">Invertebrates</h3>

<p>Two phases [22,31,43,53,54]:</p>

<ol>
  <li>short-term memory: protein and RNA synthesis-independent lasts mins to hours</li>
  <li>long-term memory: protein and RNA synthesis-dependent that lasts several hours to days, weeks, etc</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="hebb">Hebb</h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>wealth of evidence demonstrated that cell assemblies work together to represent information in the brain [57]. no single memory “center” exists.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="cellular-and-systems-consolidation">Cellular and systems consolidation</h2>

<p>Types types:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Synaptic/cellular consolidation: Fast molecular and cellular events occurring early after training and lasting no more than several hours to a few days in particular brain regions engaged in acquisition and early processing of new information</li>
  <li>Systems consolidation: Slow and entails the participation of neo-cortical regions and their interactions with the MTL that reorganize the recently learned material</li>
</ol>

<p>Note that if consolidation of new information involves interactions with an already stored associative “schema” systems consolidation can be rapid [89].</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>systems and cellular consolidation are interdependent, because the synaptic consolidation product (a stable memory trace in the hippocampus) must last long enough to permit systems consolidation processes to work</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="lesion-imaging-and-pharmacological-evidence-for-system-consolidation">Lesion, imaging, and pharmacological evidence for system consolidation</h2>

<p>Mostly MTL lesions lead to a graded retrograde amnesia with recent memories spared. However, these lesions lead to ungraded (flat) retrograde amnesia for spatial memory in the Morris water maze.</p>

<h3 id="time-lag">Time Lag</h3>

<p>Gist is that it takes time to get to LTM but in certain cases it can be immediate.</p>

<p>Takshami et al [82] find the largest decrease in hippocampal activity (and increase in vmPFC activity) between days 1 and 2, an interval of time without a decrease in memory performance.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>for certain learning tasks new information is consolidated and stored in neocortical structures from the time of training and this is needed for memory recall [10,21,44-46,60,89]</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="acc">ACC</h3>

<p>In article say that question of ACC’s involvement in storage vs retrieval is unanswered. It has been known to be involved with retrieval of remote memories [33,58], although from some other stuff I saw it was possible that the ACC came online only to resolve difficult to remember things or stuff that was being forget…so it was more involved in cognitive control and less with particular memory processes [Rudy et al., 72].</p>

<h3 id="late-consolidation">Late Consolidation</h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>We are tempted to suggest that rather than looking for specific sites of late consolidation of a particular learning experience, it might be wiser to view consolidation as the result of complex interactions between different brain regions, each using its own sequence of molecular and cellular events.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>the hippocampus more engaged in rapid encoding of events and their sequence while detailed memory representations are likely contained within distributed neocortical areas [30] but see [61]</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>it is surprising the paucity of work done to unravel the neurobiological bases of experience-induced cortical reorganization (58 for references)</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="alternate-view-to-standard-model">Alternate view to standard model</h2>

<h3 id="multiple-trace-theory">Multiple trace theory</h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>hippocampus is essential for the storage and retrieval of detailed episodic and spatial memories independently of the age of the memory</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>however, semantic memories and schematic representations of the topography are hippocampus-independent.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>in other words, insofar as memories represent detailed information, they are dependent on hippocampal circuits.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So with replay of memories that are observed, the multiple trace theory would predict that a new trace would be generated within the hippocampus, whereas the standard model would say that there is a reorganization in cortical areas to better process this information.</p>

<h3 id="other-theories">Other Theories</h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>one theory proposes that remote memories are stored in the neocortex, but the hippocampus retains a critical role in their retrieval [86]. here, the hippocampus does not contain the memory trace representing an experience but it provides an index that enables the trace to be retrieved.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>other theory proposes that new information is consolidated and stored solely in the hippocampus [51,63]</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="persistence-of-long-term-memory-storage">Persistence of long-term memory storage</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>Few works have assessed the involvement of the hippocampus in memory persistence, probably because of the dominant idea that the hippocampus appears to have a temporary role in memory storage [98]; see [33] for references.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>first study that demonstrated a lasting process in the hippocampus required for LTM consolidation…[70]…found that hippocampal neural activity is needed for consolidation/storage of spatial info during 5 days after training rats in a water maze.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>mounting evidence that different types of glutamate receptors undergo long-lasting changes and/or are needed at very late post-training time points in the hippocampus [16,70,76]</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>it is feasible that these long-lasting changes may well facilitate reactivations of the hippocampal circuit and may entrain extrahippocampal structures in which the memory trace is eventually stored.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>several findings suggest that the persistence of memory trace for the first several days post learning is important in establishing remote memories [76,93].</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I view this as possibly suggesting that replay at the initial periods are important in solidifying the memory, which will dependent on changes in cortical synaptic plasticity and morphology.</p>

<h3 id="persistence-of-the-initial-trace">Persistence of the initial trace</h3>

<p>A prediction of the standard model is that the hippocampal memory trace guides systems consolidation. To do so, the memory index in the hippocampus must last long enough to permit the initial steps of memory trace consolidation in the neocortex. In this context, persistence might be viewed as the process by which a “persistent” hippocampal trace enables the transfer of information to the cortex and the stabilization of this information.</p>

<h3 id="persistence-in-the-hippocampus">Persistence in the hippocampus</h3>

<p>It appears that BDNF appears to be important [7].</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We also propose that LTM storage is achieved by recurrent rounds of consolidation-like protein synthesis-dependent processes and that induction of BDNF expression at this critical time point is important for the initiation of a cascade of molecular and cellular events that leads to synaptic remodeling and growth of new synaptic connections which are involved in various forms of LTM [6,49]</p>
</blockquote>

<p>One thing not mentioned here is the prior hypothesis and those silent RNA things. Still need to look at those papers to get a more detailed understanding. However, regardless of those particular details, it appears persistence of the hippocampal trace in the initial hours/days is needed for a later process that produces the LTM.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Girardeau 2011]]></title>
    <link href="http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/blog/2014/01/05/girardeau-2011/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-05T17:08:46-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/blog/2014/01/05/girardeau-2011</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Basically this article suggests that a mechanism for consolidation can consistent of sharp wave-ripples that occur periodically in slow-wave fluctuations. The bursts of activity that occur with these ripples may act to ‘reinforce’ recent experiences and engage more long-term memory storage machinery. For instance, this strong firing could turn on some prion-like machinery that leads to persistent maintenance of memory-induced changes in the circuitry.</p>

<h2 id="stage-model-of-memory-formation">2-Stage Model of Memory Formation</h2>

<p>Based on Buzsaki’s work [see 6,7], they describe memory formation as </p>

<blockquote>
  <ol>
    <li>novel information is first encoded during the waking state</li>
    <li>then consolidated during subsequent sleep</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<p>During alert wakefulness [see 8]:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>higher levels of neuromodulators such as acetylcholine in the hippocampus enhance the influence of external inputs relative to intrinsic activity, likely favoring sensory processing and predominant information flow from the neocortex to the hippocampus</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="sharp-wave-ripples-swprs">Sharp Wave-Ripples (SWPRs)</h2>

<p>Happens during slow wave sleep and quiet wakefulness. Massive endogenous activation of large neuronal populations at repeated but irregular intervals that</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Provide the strong synaptic bombardment necessary for the induction of long term synaptic changes</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Occur at 0.01-2HZ and when they occur they have high population frequency of firing (150-200Hz). More details about how the ripples, propogate through the hippocampus are found in the paper.</p>

<p>[TODO: add some of the figures from the paper]</p>

<h2 id="replay-and-synaptic-plasticity">Replay and Synaptic Plasticity</h2>

<p>Relate SWPRs to replay and off-line memory consolidation.</p>

<p><span class="fluo">I wonder if the ripples particularly the slow-wave stuff can be measured with fMRI? Or maybe that is what we are measuring during awake consolidation? </span></p>

<p><p class='info info' data-title='Question'>I wonder if the ripples particularly the slow-wave stuff can be measured with fMRI? Or maybe that is what we are measuring during awake consolidation?</p></p>

<p>The idea here is that weakly depolarized cells during encoding can then lead to a persistent memory by strong replay later. It appears that this replay does happen during slow-wave sleep (SWS) [see 44-46]. Reactivations would involve broader brain regions, including the thalamus and neocortex.</p>

<p>One issue here is that many of these studies were done on highly trained animals so learning per say did not occur.</p>

<h2 id="swprs-and-consolidation">SWPRs and Consolidation</h2>

<p>Suppressing the ripples impairs consolidation [57].</p>

<h2 id="hippocampo-neocortical-information-transfer">Hippocampo-Neocortical Information Transfer</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>Successful retrieval becomes increasingly dependent on neocortical areas, in particular the prefrontal and anterior cingulate cortices [see 59,60]</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="slow-or-fast">Slow or Fast?</h3>

<p>Unclear however if this transition from hippocampus to neocortex is always slow with some evidence of rapid consolidation when new information is incorporated into a pre-existing cortical network of similar traces (i.e., a schema) [63].</p>

<h3 id="oscillations">Oscillations</h3>

<p>Initial encoding is done at theta oscillations for transfer between hippocampus and superficial layers of retrohippocampal  (entorhinal, subicular, presubicular, and parasubicular) areas. In the deep layers of the retrohippocampal cortices, which relay hippocampal outputs to the neocortex, are modulated by SPWRs.</p>

<h2 id="awake-replay">Awake Replay?</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>Most reactivations during awake SPWRs occur in reverse order when the animal receives a water reward at the end of a trajectory [80], reactivations were also found to anticipate the subsequent trajectory (in forward order) when the animal was about to start running again [84].</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Suggestion is made that maybe awake replay plays a slightly different role in consolidation…although it is unclear what that difference is to me.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Neuronal sequences corresponding to remote trajectories [86] as well as routes never experience before (‘shortcuts’) [88] have also been reported.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="synaptic-downscaling-alternate-hypothesis">Synaptic Downscaling (Alternate Hypothesis)</h2>

<p>Posits that </p>

<blockquote>
  <p>SWS promotes a global synaptic downscaling necessary to avoid saturation of synaptic strengths [90,91].</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s interesting that this hypothesis is consistent with that other paper [todo: find] that finds greater resting connectivity in memory retrieval related areas in the evening than in the morning.</p>

<p>However, a problem with the downscaling hypothesis is that</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>it would predict a progressive increase in firing rates during the awake state, followed by a commensurate decrease during sleep. yet, the overall firing rate in the hippocampus is maintained over time.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This issue is great for me as it provides a potentially contrasting hypothesis on what might be expected to occur over the course of awake consolidation.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Arshavsky 2006]]></title>
    <link href="http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/blog/2013/12/30/arshavsky-2006/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-30T22:26:55-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/blog/2013/12/30/arshavsky-2006</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This article puts forth the hypothesis that long-term consolidation occurs via modification of DNA in individual neurons. I wonder if an alternative to having DNA explain the persistence of a memory trace is the replay of memories that occurs during system consolidation. One can imagine if the neural system loops over the same trace, it potentially can strengthen the connections via synaptic consolidation over time. Furthermore, sleep might help do this same thing, replay or refresh different memories to allow for continual maintenance.</p>

<p>For work on the stability of synaptic connections see Grutzendler et al., 2002; Zuo et al., 2005; De Paola et al., 2006.</p>

<h2 id="flaws-in-model">Flaws In Model</h2>

<p>He begins with a discussion about how the traditional model can’t explain how you can retain your old memories when you have an epileptic seizure since this should change all your memories. Similarly he claims it’s difficult to understand how something that is ever-changing like proteins maintaining the memories of those who can remember almost everything.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Since proteins have a very short lifetime as compared with memory lifetime, additional hypotheses are required to explain how stable synaptic modifications could result from a transient activation of the protein synthesis.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>He then strangely claims that</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>…memory reactivation must lead to further modification in synaptic connections and, eventually, to memory erosion, in direct correlation to how frequently it is accessed.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>and concludes</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Since this is not the case, and repetitive retrievals lead to memory strengthening rather than erosion, we must conclude that memory is resistant to the synaptic activity that accompanies memory retrieval.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This conclusion is strange because I thought that was the point, repeated retrieval and encoding leads to strengthening of the connection via reactivation and the hebbian rule.</p>

<p>Another bad example, he gives is about the issue of spontaneous neural activity.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>According to SPH, we must expect that ongoing spontaneous activity will lead to incessant, uncontrolled modifications in synaptic connections, and eventually, to erosions in older memories.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>But the glitch in his argument is that spontaneous activity happens amongst the current connections. True there is some noise but really this might strengthen the already existent connections.</p>

<p>Another oddity is that he claims that</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>…memory retrieval cannot occur through the reactivation of the same neural assemblies that are involved in initial learning, because these two processes have different localizations</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Yes, but it isn’t cut and dry like this. Instead the weights just shift from hippocampus to neocortex, the hippocampus can still be involved. Also even for a recent memory, the involvement of the hippocampus is accompanied by involved of distal neocortical regions.</p>

<p>But I think the claim is just that:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>…primary synaptic consolidation in the MTL and persistent system consolidation in the neocortex may have radically different mechanisms.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>He does raise some interesting points about how issues with Alzheimer’s isn’t related to LTP stuff. Not sure if he is missing some facts like structural changes that occur with synaptic consolidation.</p>

<h2 id="dna-hypothesis">DNA Hypothesis</h2>

<p>I don’t totally get this hypothesis as he doesn’t explain the mechanism that clearly. It seems like it would have something to do with somatic DNA recombination. And he notes that</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>blockage of enzymes participating in the process of somatic DNA recombination impairs learning and memory consolidation (Colon-Cesario et al., 2006; McGowan et al., 2004; Pena de Ortiz et al., 2003; Ren and Pena de Ortiz, 2002; Wang et al., 2003).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Another hypothesis states that</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Epigenetic modifications alter the structure of the chromatin due to chemical changes to the DNA or histones without change the DNA nucleotide sequence…(Chwang et al., 2005; Levenson et al., 2004)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don’t totally get how these processes can’t be altered or undone. For instance, shouldn’t additional consolidation eventually alter these DNA-related modifications?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Making memories last: the synaptic tagging and capture hypothesis]]></title>
    <link href="http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/blog/2013/12/29/redondo-2011/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-29T15:14:34-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/blog/2013/12/29/redondo-2011</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This article is specific to cellular levels of consolidation and so a bunch of it isn’t relevant to my work. The theory of synaptic and capture has some interesting associations. First, the idea that the moment after encoding requires critical events for persisting the memory. How exactly this memory persists can involve some different options (e.g., BDNF is sufficient on its own). Second, is a link to factors such as novelty (release dopamine) and context (?) that we know are important on the systems level but here we can understand a cellular basis. For instance, in the case of a prior context or schema, this might more quickly lead to tagging of the new element in that context/schema, which provides a greater likelihood that the new item will be remembered.</p>

<p>One thing I wonder if maintenance of some of these cellular processes is dependent on re-play. That is without the replay, there would be some degradation. Now there isn’t much work here that pertains to this, however we should note that with the fMRI when we measure replay it happens within the time-window for synaptic consolidation. So a few possibilities exist here, the replay at the systems level occurs independently of the cellular or that there is some synergy or one is required for the other…TODO: think through this.</p>

<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2>

<p>An initial point in the article that I like is that the memory trace is distributed.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>specific memory traces are not stored within individual neurons, still less at a single synaptic within individual neurons, still less at a single synaptic location, but are distributed in an overlapping manner   across multiple neurons and synapses.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The article however focuses I think on more local processes specifically the cellular components of consolidation. It discusses the fact that a synapse can have a possibility for LTM but persistence requires additional factors that happen after encoding.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A core concept of the STC hypothesis is that memory encoding creates the potential for LTM but is noncommittal with respect to whether persistent memory will actually occur (FIG. 1).</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>determining the fate of successive memories only at the time of encoding would be extremely complicated.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="original-stc-hypothesis">Original STC Hypothesis</h2>

<p>LTP has the following steps: </p>

<ol>
  <li>the expression of synaptic potentiation with the setting of a local synaptic tag;</li>
  <li>the synthesis and distribution of plasticity-related proteins (PrPs); </li>
  <li>the capture of these proteins by tagged synapses; </li>
  <li>the ultimate stabilization of synaptic strength. if the prior activity history of the neuron has upregulated the availability of PrPs in a particular dendritic compartment, these will be captured by local synaptic tags and so ensure the sta- bilization of the synaptic component of a new memory trace soon after it is encoded</li>
</ol>

<p>Thus, the prior or subsequent context of the animal will be very important as to whether a memory trace is stored.</p>

<h2 id="challenges">Challenges</h2>

<p>The paper then discusses how some of these steps don’t necessarily need to follow one another (e.g., E-LTP can coexist with a state in which a synaptic tag has not been set or has been blocked) and some other issues.</p>

<p>For instance, slow-onset LTP can also lead to memory being encoding/stored. </p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Slow-onset LTP is also seen following place cell activity replay, in which patterns of two place cells recorded during exploration of an environment are used as inputs for in vitro experiments in spike timing-dependent plasticity.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There’s also a dissociation between functional changes in synaptic strength and structural changes but simply a change in the structure alone is insufficient for long-term LTP.</p>

<h2 id="revised-stc-hypothesis">Revised STC Hypothesis</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>The induction of E-LTP trigger two separate processes — one associated with increasing the functional strength of the synapse, the other with altering the structure of the synapse. When these occur alone, only a transitory change in synaptic strength is observed. However, when accompanied by the delivery of PRPs, a more lasting increase in synaptic strength occurs.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Arrival and capture of PRPs is essential for stabilization. Without them, any change will go backwards.</p>

<p>Remember that tagging occurs for the synapse and not a particular molecule.</p>

<h3 id="limitation">Limitation</h3>

<p>This is still only for in vitro and links missing for in vivo, although it’s assumed that same processes work for in vivo.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Clopath 2012]]></title>
    <link href="http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/blog/2013/12/28/clopath-2012/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-28T17:11:11-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://czarrar.github.io/prospectus/blog/2013/12/28/clopath-2012</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For reference details see <a href="/bibliography/Clopath_2012jo.html">Details</a> or the brief reference at the end <a href="#Clopath:2012jo">(Clopath, 2012)</a>.</p>

<h2 id="model">Model</h2>

<p>The article discusses a synaptic plasticity model, which has three steps:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Tagging:</strong> The synapse strength is the sum of two parts, the weight of the early phase and the weight of the late phase. The early weight can be in a neutral state, high state, or low state. If the early weight is in a high state or low state, it is automatically tagged. The state of the early weight switches from neutral to high with a probability given by a Hebbian rule for the induction of plasticity.</li>
  <li><strong>Trigger:</strong> If the number of tags exceeds a threshold, plasticity-related proteins are synthesized. The threshold depends on the phasic dopamine level, such that if dopamine is high, the threshold is lowered. Can see this effect, if place a rat in inhibitory avoidance training following being in a novel environment. That is novelty can lower this threshold.</li>
  <li><strong>Consolidation:</strong> The late weight of the synapse is a continuous variable with two stable states. If plasticity-related proteins are available and if the synapse is tagged, the late-weight will go to the upper stable state if eLTP was induced, lower if eLTD was induced.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="limitations">Limitations</h2>

<p>They mention in the article “On a higher level, it is not clear how this synaptic consolidation is linked to the consolidation by transferring memories from different brain areas typically happening during rest and sleep”. This is important…it’s unclear to me as well. The article does draw some links between synapse and more psychological concepts (e.g., dopamine levels related to the novelty and the likelihood to consolidate memories).</p>

<h2 id="future-thoughts">Future Thoughts</h2>

<p>I’m wondering if the synaptic tagging model could have analogues to schema representation in the mPFC. It’s been shown that learning of congruent information is processed in the mPFC <a href="#vanKesteren:2012hj">(van Kesteren, Ruiter, Fernández and Henson, 2012)</a> and this area shows up-regulation of memory relevant genes in the rat immediately after learning <a href="#Tse:2011ee">(Tse, Takeuchi, Kakeyama, Kajii, Okuno, Tohyama, Bito and Morris, 2011)</a>. This suggests that information is tagged both here in the mPFC and in the hippocampus for schema representations along with increases in activity. The combination of increased activity (akin to LTP) and genetic up-regulation (akin to synaptic tagging), we might expect long-term memory storage.</p>

<h2 id="references">References</h2>

<p><ol class="bibliography"><li><span id="vanKesteren:2012hj">van Kesteren, M.T.R., Ruiter, D.J., Fernández, G., Henson, R.N., 2012. How schema and novelty augment memory formation.. Trends in Neurosciences 35, 211–219.</span><a class="details" href="/bibliography/vanKesteren_2012hj.html">Details</a></li>
<li><span id="Tse:2011ee">Tse, D., Takeuchi, T., Kakeyama, M., Kajii, Y., Okuno, H., Tohyama, C., Bito, H., Morris, R.G.M., 2011. Schema-dependent gene activation and memory encoding in neocortex.. Science (New York, NY) 333, 891–895.</span><a class="details" href="/bibliography/Tse_2011ee.html">Details</a></li>
<li><span id="Clopath:2012jo">Clopath, C., 2012. Synaptic consolidation: an approach to long-term learning.. Cognitive neurodynamics 6, 251–257.</span><a class="details" href="/bibliography/Clopath_2012jo.html">Details</a></li>
<li><span id="Redondo:2011bp">Redondo, R.L., Morris, R.G.M., 2011. Making memories last: the synaptic tagging and capture hypothesis.. Nature Reviews: Neuroscience 12, 17–30.</span><a class="details" href="/bibliography/Redondo_2011bp.html">Details</a></li></ol></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
